<!--

    Copyright (c) 2009-2016 Wilfred Springer

    Permission is hereby granted, free of charge, to any person
    obtaining a copy of this software and associated documentation
    files (the "Software"), to deal in the Software without
    restriction, including without limitation the rights to use,
    copy, modify, merge, publish, distribute, sublicense, and/or sell
    copies of the Software, and to permit persons to whom the
    Software is furnished to do so, subject to the following
    conditions:

    The above copyright notice and this permission notice shall be
    included in all copies or substantial portions of the Software.

    THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED "AS IS", WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND,
    EXPRESS OR IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO THE WARRANTIES
    OF MERCHANTABILITY, FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE AND
    NONINFRINGEMENT. IN NO EVENT SHALL THE AUTHORS OR COPYRIGHT
    HOLDERS BE LIABLE FOR ANY CLAIM, DAMAGES OR OTHER LIABILITY,
    WHETHER IN AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, TORT OR OTHERWISE, ARISING
    FROM, OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE SOFTWARE OR THE USE OR
    OTHER DEALINGS IN THE SOFTWARE.

-->
<article>
  <articleinfo>
    <title>Under The Hood</title>
    <subtitle>What's going on behind the scenes?</subtitle>
    <releaseinfo><?eval $pom.version?></releaseinfo>
    <author>
      <firstname>Wilfred</firstname>
      <surname>Springer</surname>
    </author>
  </articleinfo>
  <para>
    The previous chapter introduced a couple of simple introductory
    cases, showing some of the tricks the framework has up its sleeves
    if you do not feel the desire to customize anything. While you
    were reading that chapter, you might have already gone like "hmmm,
    that's sweet, but unfortunately it doesn't work in my corner
    case". If that's what you thought, then this is the chapter you
    need.
  </para>
  <para>
    In this chapter, I will explain what is actually going on under
    the hood, in order to understand how to extend the framework
    yourself. The focus in this chapter is on four major abstractions:
    the Codec interface itself, the CodecFactory interface, the
    Binding interface and the CodecDecorator interface. In addition to
    discussing the actual interface, this chapter will also discuss
    some of the implementations, in order to help you to understand
    how everything fits together.
  </para>

  <section>
    <title>Codec</title>
    <para>
      Let's first revisit the Codec interface. In the previous
      chapter, we already talked about the way you use this
      interface. In fact, we said that you better use the Codecs
      convenience class in all cases. If you do that, then there is
      actually very little to know about the Codec interface
      itself. It just magically works.
    </para>
    <para>
      However, if you want to extend the framework yourself, then this
      is the
      <emphasis>first</emphasis>
      interface you really need to
      understand, since this is probably the interface you need to
      implement.
    </para>
    <figure id="fig-codec-interface">
      <?dbfo keep-together="auto"?>
      <title>Codec Interface</title>
      <programlisting language="java">
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
                    href="Codec.java"
                    parse="text"/>
      </programlisting>
    </figure>
    <para>
      The
      <methodname>decode(BitBuffer, Resolver,
        Builder)
      </methodname>
      is obviously the operation that will
      decode data from the
      <interfacename>BitBuffer</interfacename>
      into an instance of<classname>T</classname>.
    </para>
    <para>
      The
      <interfacename>Resolver</interfacename>
      allows the
      <interfacename>Codec</interfacename>
      to resolve references used
      in Preon annotations.
    </para>
    <para>
      The Codec interface is the interface
      implemented by objects that are able to decode data from a
      BitBuffer and to encode data into a BitBuffer
      <footnote>
        <para>
          The latter is currently not supported yet, but it's not
          unlikely that it's going to be implemented in the future.
        </para>
      </footnote>
      . In addition to that, the Codec needs to be able to
      make some sort of prediction on the number of bits occupied by
      the encoded data. And last but not least, the Codec needs to be
      able to return a CodecDescriptor, used for rendering documents
      with a description of the Codec.
    </para>
    <para>
      When I just said that Codecs are capable of decoding data from a
      BitBuffer, you could have actually read 'decoding an object from
      a BitBuffer'. Codecs are associated to a single type, and are
      expected to return only a single instances of that type from the
      BitBuffer.
    </para>
    <para>
      In many cases, your objects will hold references to many other
      objects. Does that mean that a single Codec needs to be able to
      recursively traverse the object graph and understand how to
      decode each of the individual members of the objects that it
      encounters?
    </para>
    <para>
      The answer to that question is both yes and no. "Yes", since
      whenever you invoke decode on the Codec, it needs to be able to
      reproduce all objects that are referenced by the object that is
      going to be returned. "No", since the Codec does not have to
      understand all of that itself. It can simply delegate to other
      Codecs, one for every type of attribute it encounters.
    </para>
    <para>
      If you are decoding an object, you
      <emphasis>could</emphasis>
      actually use the Codec interface directly. If you create an
      instance using the
      <classname>Codecs</classname>
      class, they
      just magically know what to do. We just learned that Codecs
      constructed like this, will most likely delegate their work to
      other Codecs, which in turn will most likely delegate their work
      to other Codecs, and so on and so forth. This way, the Codec
      both
      <emphasis>hides</emphasis>
      a chain of responsibility, but
      is also able to act as a
      <emphasis>link</emphasis>
      inside a
      chain of responsibility.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>CodecFactory</title>
    <para>
      The previous section ended with stating that a single Codec most
      likely delegates to other Codecs, which in turn delegate to
      other Codecs, etc. Obviously, each Codec has to be constructed
      before it can be used. All of these instances are created as a
      result of the create() method on Codecs. But how does the Codecs
      class know which ones to create?
    </para>
    <para>
      As you might have already have guessed by its name, it is of
      course the CodecFactory. The CodecFactory a single operation,
      that is expected to be able to return Codec from the context
      passed in, or return<literal>null</literal>.
    </para>
    <figure id="fig-codecfactory-interface">
      <title>CodecFactory Interface</title>
      <programlisting language="java"><?dbfo keep-together="auto"?>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
                    href="CodecFactory.java"
                    parse="text"/>
      </programlisting>
    </figure>
    <para>
      Almost every type of Codec you will ever use, will be created by
      a CodecFactory. If you are searching the Preon codebase for the
      different type of Codecs supported by it, then chances are you
      will stumble across CodecFactories only. And if you want to
      extend the framework with your own Codecs, the thing you
      actually need to pass to the Codecs class is a CodecFactory, and
      not a Codec.
    </para>
    <para>
      The CodecFactory needs to be able to create a Codec from three
      parameters passed in. The type of object expected, a socalled
      ResolverContext and metadata. If the Codec is used to decode
      data to be injected in a field, then the metadata provides
      access to the annotations defined on that field
      <footnote>
        <para>
          In general, the CodecFactory should not rely on the assumption
          that the metadata passed in is based on a field. It should
          just treat it as a number of hints suggesting how to decode
          data.
        </para>
      </footnote>
      .
    </para>
    <para>
      The third parameter (ResolverContext) is a Limbo
      ReferenceContext. This is the object that supports your
      CodecFactory in creating references to the context of the field
      for which it is currently trying to create a reference.
    </para>
    <example id="example-things">
      <title>Expression sample</title>
      <programlisting><![CDATA[class Stuff {
  @Bound int nrOfThings;
  @BoundList(size="nrThings") Thing[] things;
}]]></programlisting>
    </example>
    <para>
      Let's take the class above as an example, and assume that your
      CodecFactory needs to see if it is able to construct a Codec for
      the "things" field. The annotation contains an expression
      defining the number of "things" in the array. However, the
      <envar>size</envar>
      annotation attribute is just a String.
    </para>
    <para>
      In order to be able to turn the expresion "nrOfThings" into
      something usable, we need to turn that expression into something
      we can actually evaluate - in this case, a Limbo Expression
      object. And if there is a problem with this expression, we
      obviously want to find out early.
    </para>
    <figure id="fig-expr-relevance">
      <title>Expression applied</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="src/docbkx/things-sample.png" width="13cm"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>
      There are basically two things that could be wrong with the
      expression: either the expression cannot be interpreted, or the
      expression contains references to variables not available in the
      context in which the expression will be evaluated. The
      ResolverContext supports detecting the latter case.
    </para>
    <para>
      This is the way it works: whenever your CodecFactory gets a
      chance to create a Codec based on metadata, type information and
      a ResolverContext passed in, it will have to use the
      ResolverContext to create Expression objects. The Expressions
      class used to create Expression instances accepts a
      ReferenceContext as a parameter, and ResolverContext is nothing
      but a special ReferenceContext. (One specific to Preon.)
      Normally, you would pass the ResolverContext directly, but there
      are cases in which you could consider replacing or wrapping the
      ResolverContext
      <footnote>
        <para>
          There are actually cases in which you might want to replace
          that ResolverContext with another one. Typically when you want
          to
          <emphasis>introduce</emphasis>
          new variables, or if you are
          basically 'popping' or 'pushing' the stack. (If your current
          context changes into the context of the attributes type.)
        </para>
      </footnote>
      .
    </para>
    <para>
      So, the first and most important purpose of the ResolverContext
      is early validation of your expression. The second and also
      important purpose of the ResolverContext is to facilitate
      <emphasis>documentation</emphasis>
      getting generated from your
      Codec.
    </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>If</emphasis>
      your CodecFactory constructs a Codec
      based on an expression, then the documentation generated by that
      Codec probably needs to take that into account.
    </para>
    <para>
      In case of the example of<xref linkend="fig-expr-relevance"/>,
      you would expect a description similar to this: "First you read
      a 32-bit integer. Then you read a list of items with the size
      corresponding to the 32-bit integer you just read before."
    </para>
    <para>
      Any type of realistic documentation of this file format needs to
      include this dependency. You want the documentation to clearly
      state that the size of the list size is dependent on the 32 bits
      you just read before. That last bit "the 32 bits you just read
      before" is encapsulated in a Reference. And the ResolverContext
      allows the Expressions class to obtain these references without
      having to analyze the entire class again.
    </para>
    <para>
      So, the Expression "nrOfElements" will be parsed into a
      Reference to the nrOfElements attribute defined before. It's the
      responsibility of the Reference to render itself in a useful
      way. The Codec or CodecFactory does not even
      <emphasis>try</emphasis>
      to make sense out of it. It just relies
      on the ResolverContext to return a proper reference.
    </para>
    <programlisting><![CDATA[
Expression expr = Expressions.create("nrOfElements", resolverContext);
// Potentially results in" 
// "the number of elements defined before"
expr.document(....); 
    ]]></programlisting>
    <para>
      Now, this may be one of the areas in which the flexibility is
      getting a litle in the way of understanding what's going on
      here. However, just to comfort you a little, it's just object
      orientation. That's all it is. The Reference
      <emphasis>itself</emphasis>
      decides how it needs to be
      represented. And the type of ResolverContext passed to the Codec
      decides how these References are getting constructed. With that,
      sky is the limit.
    </para>
    <section>
      <title>CompoundCodecFactory</title>
      <para>
        The CompoundCodecFactory must be one of the only implementations
        of CodecFactory that doesn't actually create any other Codec
        itself. The main purpose of the CompoundCodecFactory is to hide
        the complexity of choosing a particular type of CodecFactory
        behind an interface. The CompoundCodecFactory references a list
        of other CodecFactories. When asked for construction of a Codec,
        it will simply ask all of the factories it references and try
        each of them to construct a Codec. If all fails, it will simply
        return<literal>null</literal>, just what you would expect for a
        CodecFactory.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>WholeNumberCodecFactory</title>
      <para>
        There are many CodecFactories that create Codecs
        themselves. (There are also a few other CodecFactories that
        don't create Codecs themselves, apart from the
        CompoundCodecFactory, but that's a subject that can wait for a
        while while.) This section starts with one of the most
        simplest: the WholeNumberCodecFactory.
      </para>
      <para>
        The WholeNumberCodecFactory creates Codecs capable of decoding -
        well - whole numbers. I didn't want to say integers, since that
        might lead you to be believe that its capable of decoding
        java.lang.Integer and its primitive counterpart only, which is
        not the case. WholeNumberCodecFactory supports decoding byte,
        short, int, long and all object representations of those types.
      </para>
      <para>
        The WholeNumberCodecFactory is the first example in which a
        a CodecFactory could use the metadata passed with annotations to
        decode the data in the proper way. By default, it will return a
        Codec for byte, short, int or long type of fields whenever:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <literal>null</literal>
            is passed in as metadata;
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            An @Bound instance is passed in as metadata;
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            An @BoundNumber instance is passed in as metadata.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
        The
        <literal>null</literal>
        case is not important for now. The
        @Bound annotation supports the default case. The CodecFactory
        will take this annotation as a signal that it actually needs to
        create a Codec, using the defaults for the type passed in. The
        @BoundNumber annotation supports the case in which you
        <emphasis>do</emphasis>
        want a Codec to be created, but you
        don't like the defaults.
      </para>
      <para>
        Here are some examples in which you would want to use the
        @BoundNumber annotation, instead of the @Bound annatation:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            You want to decode 4 bits into a byte.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            You want to force little endian when decoding an 32-bit
            integer.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            You want to decode a 32-bit unsigned integer as a long.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
        The WholeNumberCodecFactory is a good example of the pattern
        that you will find implemented in almost all other
        CodecFactories:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Attempt to return a default Codec whenever
            <literal>null</literal>
            or @Bound is passed in.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            ...unless there is some other piece of metadata passed in,
            telling the CodecFactory how to customize the Codec it
            creates.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>BooleanCodecFactory</title>
      <para>
        The BooleanCodecFactory is by far the simplest example of a
        CodecFactory (and associated Codec) that you could ever come
        up with. If the CodecFactory is challenged with a boolean type
        (either the primitive type or the object type) and the
        presence of an @Bound annotation in the metadata passed in,
        then it will create a new Codec. Whenever this Codec is asked
        to decode a value from the BitBuffer, it will read a single
        bit and return true if the bit is 1, and false otherwise.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>ObjectCodecFactory</title>
      <para>
        In theory, it could have been possible to construct Codecs by
        hand, by using a constructor. However, that's not actually
        something you want to do yourself. The Codec created would have
        to closely resemble the datastructure you need to decode. And
        since every Codec is capable of decoding one value, and there is
        a fair chance that the object you are trying to decode exists of
        many other objects, it would even be quite hard to do this
        yourself.
      </para>
      <para>
        The good news is: you don't have to do all of that
        yourself. The ObjectCodecFactory basically does it all for you.
      </para>
      <para>
        The ObjectCodecFactory works on basically all existing
        objects. If all other CodecFactories fail, then the
        ObjectCodecFactory might still be able to return a Codec, even
        though the Codec created might basically be a no-op. (It won't
        decode anything.) That's why normally every CompoundCodecFactory
        instance is advised to try the ObjectCodecFactory as a last
        attempt.
      </para>
      <para>
        The ObjectCodecFactory is probably much simpler than you would
        expect. Suppose that you want to create a decoder for instances
        of type A:
      </para>
      <procedure>
        <step>
          <para>
            Get the list of all fields declared on type A.
          </para>
        </step>
        <step id="step-create-codec">
          <para>
            For each field declared on type A, create a Codec for the type of
            value accepted by that field, and wrap both the reference to
            the field and the Codec for its values in a new Binding
            instance.
          </para>
        </step>
        <step>
          <para>
            Create a new Codec that - on an invocation of decode - will
            always create an instance of type A, and populate its data
            by giving every Binding the opportunity to load its data
            from the BitBuffer passed in. (The Binding will simply use
            the Codec it references to do the actual decoding of the
            field's value.)
          </para>
        </step>
      </procedure>
      <para>
        You may have wondered how the ObjectCodecFactory creates a Codec
        corresponding to the field's type, in<xref
              linkend="step-create-codec"/>. The answer is simple: it uses a
        CodecFactory. It may be different CodecFactory than the
        ObjectCodecFactory itself, but it's highly likely that it
        references the ObjectCodecFactory itself somewhere under its
        covers.
      </para>
      <para>
        We just said that ObjectCodecFactories use Binding objects
        under the covers. It's important that you know about these
        guys, since the ObjectCodecFactory actually allows you to
        override the way they work, by pluging in your own
        BindingFactory. We are not going to discuss the typical use
        case yet, but for now it's important at least to know they
        exist. (Check out
        <xref
                linkend="section-conditional-binding"/>
        for a typical example
        on how to leverage this plugpoint.)
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>ListCodecFactory</title>
      <para>
        With the three CodecFactories listed above, we would already be
        able to decode nested objects, in which each of the objects
        fields references either a numberic value or another object. But
        that's not enough. (In fact, we don't even know when it would be
        enough; that's why Preon is an extensible framework. We leave
        it up to you to decide when you consider it to be enough.)
      </para>
      <para>
        One of the most important missing cases is support for
        lists. Many binary encoding standards have some repeating
        sequences inside. This is where the ListCodecFactory comes in.
      </para>
      <para>
        The ListCodecFactory allows you to decode lists of objects. At
        this stage, it's limited to a list of a certain size, but it is
        expected that there will be other implementations that have
        other ways to demarcate the end of the list.
      </para>
      <para>
        The ListCodecFactory creates a Codec whenever the @BoundList
        annotation is passed in. It will use the attributes of this
        annotation to figure out how and what to decode. In the simple
        case, that could be as little as stating the type and the size
        of the list.
      </para>
      <para>
        If you would create a Codec simply by passing the type and the
        size of the list, then the ListCodecFactory can be expected to
        return a Codec implementation that will - on calling decode() -
        return a List implementation that allows you to visit all
        elements in the List. Don't expect one of the default
        implementations of List though. By default, the Codec created by
        the ListCodecFactory will return its own implements of List, one
        that decodes object on the fly, on demand.
      </para>
      <para>
        It is important to emphasize the difference between the Codec
        that returns the List instance, and the Codec used to decode
        elements of the List. These are two completely different
        Codecs. The Codec decoding the List is seeded with a Codec
        capable of reading the elements of the List.
        <xref
                linkend="fig-list-decodig"/>
        shows how these elements collorate
        in a real world scenario.
      </para>
      <figure id="fig-list-decoding">
        <title>Decoding a List</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section id="section-conditional-binding">
    <title>Binding</title>
    <para>
      A couple of sections back, I talked about Bindings, and how the
      Codec created by an ObjectCodecFactory uses these bindings to
      load and store values from and in a Field. I also said that you
      can customize the way these Bindings behave. This section is
      going to give you an example.
    </para>
    <para>
      Many binary formats have some conditional built into the
      specification. Here are some examples:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          If the version of the file is bigger than 400, then read
          this data structure first, otherwise continue with the next
          data structure.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          If the first bit read is 1, then read 7 bits and decode it
          as a byte; otherwise continue to read 7 + 8 bits and
          decode as a short.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
      All of these cases could have been solved by breaking out of the
      ordinary framework and implement the entire encoding/decoding
      logic yourself. That would not only be really hard, but also
      result in code that will not be self-documenting in the way
      Preon normally is.
    </para>
    <para>
      Preon takes another approach, and allows you to declaritively
      specify the conditions in which the framework should try to
      load data in bound fields, using the @If annotation. The @If
      annotation takes a single argument, which is the condition
      stated in Limbo.
    </para>
    <para>
      The reason Preon is capable of dealing with these expression is
      because it will create a
      <firstterm>Binding</firstterm>
      that is
      capable of loading data from the BitBuffer if the condition
      holds. Which is why it is sometimes convenient to have the
      ability to create your own custom Binding implementation instead
      of the default one.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>CodecDecorator</title>
    <para>
      Up til now, we have only seen examples of CodecFactories
      creating Codecs. Codecs are however not
      <emphasis>always</emphasis>
      constructed by CodecFactories. If
      you want the framework to deal with your own Codec, then there
      is another way to make it create your own Codec, which is by
      implementing the CodecDecorator interface.
    </para>
    <para>
      As you may have guessed, the CodecDecorator has something in
      common with the Decorator Pattern (see GoF). The CodecDecorator
      allows you to transparenly add additional behaviour to a Codec,
      by applying some 'decoration'. So, where the CodecFactory
      accepts the type and metadata indicating the specific Codec you
      want to construct, the CodecDecorator
      <emphasis>also</emphasis>
      accepts the Codec that should be wrapped.
    </para>

    <section>
      <title>LazyLoadingCodecDecorator</title>
      <para>
        When you ask the LazyLoadingCodecDecorator to decorate an
        existing Codec, you get a new Codec that - on receiving a call
        to decode - will
        <emphasis>not</emphasis>
        pass the call on to
        the Codec it decorates; instead, it will return a proxy that
        acts as the object that needs to be created by the decororated
        Codec. The
        <emphasis>actual</emphasis>
        object will only be
        loaded from the BitBuffer right after you call an operation on
        that proxy for the first time.
      </para>
      <para>
        The LazyLoadingCodecDecorator is triggered by the presence of
        the LazyLoading annotation on the type you want to have loaded
        lazily.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>SlicingCodecDecorator</title>
      <para>
        The SlicingCodecDecorator decorates existing Codecs by returning
        a new Codec that - on receiving a decode call - passes the
        request on to the decorated Codec, but replacing the BitBuffer
        passed by taking a slice of the original.
      </para>
      <para>
        The main reason of having a SlicingCodecDecorator is to
        support type length value records. The main idea here is that
        Codecs reading the records data should
        <emphasis>not</emphasis>
        be required to know the amount of
        data to be expected. As you might have seen before, the Codec
        constructed doesn't support passing in the maximum number of
        bytes to be read, or anything. And having to implement that
        logic for all TLV record readers seemed to be a waste.
      </para>
      <para>
        Instead of having every TLV record Codec implement support for
        detecting the end of the record, the decision was made to
        externalize that behaviour and put it into a separate Codec,
        decorating the Codec that reads the data from the TLV record.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>

</article>